Okay, Boker Tov בוקר טוב Boker Tov everybody. Today's Daf דף Daf
is,
well
today's Daf דף Daf officially is Lamed Bet ל''ב, Lamed Bet, we
are still behind, we pick up on the bottom of Lamed
Alef, Amud Bet ל''א עמוד ב' Lamed Alef, Amud Bet and what
we are dealing with is the fact that the Mishnah משנה Mishnah
deals with a case of Safek Kiddushin, Safek Gierushin ספק קידושין ספק
גירושין Safek Kiddushin, Safek Gierushin and speaks about how in that case
where there's a question if the Erva ערווה Erva is in the
picture, what you do with the Tzarat Erva צרת ערווה Tzarat Erva
is Chalitza חליצה Chalitza not Yibum יבום. Yibum. But the Gemara גמרא
Gemara distinctly points out that the case of Safek Gierushin ספק גירושין
Safek Gierushin isn't really a Safek Gierushin ספק גירושין, Safek Gierushin, it's
really a case about a Gierushin גירושין Gierushin that's Pasul D'Rabbanan פסול
דרבנן Pasul D'Rabbanan and therefore it's working with the assumption that a
classic Safek Gierushin ספק גירושין Safek Gierushin would actually not be meaningful
because the woman would retain her Chazaka חזקה Chazaka and her status
as an Eshet Ish אשת איש Eshet Ish and the co-wife, the
Tzarat Erva צרת ערווה, Tzarat Erva, would retain her status as exempt
from Yibum יבום. Yibum. And that's what the Gemara's גמרא Gemara’s working
through and the consequences of Lachmir להחמיר Lachmir and demand Chalitza חליצה.
Chalitza. We could be Machmir מחמיר Machmir in some cases without a
cost but in this case if we were Machmir מחמיר, Machmir, it
would come with a serious cost and therefore we leave it on
the D'Oraita דאורייתא D'Oraita and we say that such a woman is
considered still an Eshet Ish אשת איש Eshet Ish and her co-wife
is considered a Tzarat Erva צרת ערווה Tzarat Erva and she walks
away without Chalitza חליצה. Chalitza. So now the Gemara גמרא Gemara picks
up like this.
I am going to tell you, we are in the middle of
Lamed Alef Amud Alef ל''א עמוד א' Lamed Alef Amud Alef and
it says, the line that you see the line with the asterisk
about exactly in the middle it starts with the asterisk, it says
Hayso Omedet הייתה עומדת Hayso Omedet and we'll begin one line above
that. Begavi Gierushin בגבי גירושין Begavi Gierushin says the Gemara גמרא Gemara
when it comes to Get גט, Get, Milo Tnan מי לא תנן,
Milo Tnan, did we not have a case of a real Safek
Gierushin ספק גירושין Safek Gierushin that would have the same consequences that
the co-wife would get Chalitza חליצה? Chalitza? You're saying the co-wife just
walks away. V'Ha Tnan והתנן, V'Ha Tnan, we taught in the Mishnah
משנה Mishnah in Gittin גיטין: Gittin: Hayso Omedet Birshus Harabbim הייתה עומדת
ברשות הרבים, Hayso Omedet Birshus Harabbim, this is a classic case of
a Safek ספק, Safek, a woman was standing in the public domain
V'Zarko Lo וזרקו לה, V'Zarko Lo, Karov Lo קרוב לה Karov Lo
Megureshet מגורשת, Megureshet, Karov Lo קרוב לו Karov Lo Eina Megureshet אינה
מגורשת. Eina Megureshet. He threw a Get גט Get to his wife,
if it was closer to her she's divorced, closer to him she's
not divorced. We're not going to worry about the exact type of
Kinyan קניין Kinyan that is being referred to here. Mechtza al Mechtza
מחצה על מחצה, Mechtza al Mechtza, it's exactly midpoint, so Mechtza al
Mechtza מחצה על מחצה, Mechtza al Mechtza, Megureshet Eina Megureshet מגורשת אינה
מגורשת, Megureshet Eina Megureshet, she's divorced and not divorced, it's a doubt.
V'Amrinan ואמרינן, V'Amrinan, so that's what the Mishnah משנה Mishnah says and
then we the Gemara גמרא Gemara says what do we say? L'Mai
Hilchasa למאי הלכתא, L'Mai Hilchasa, what's the relevance of her being doubtfully
divorced? D'ee Cohen hu דאי כהן הוא, D'ee Cohen hu, Asura Lei
אסורה ליה, Asura Lei, oh my God excuse me I don't know
what this is, iPhone reacts on me, okay cellphone put it
there forgot it last time, D'ee Cohen hu דאי כהן הוא D'ee
Cohen hu that if he's a Kohen כהן Kohen she... if his
wife is a Kohenet כהנת Kohenet he cannot now decide well maybe
it wasn't a divorce, if he was a Kohen כהן Kohen he
cannot now decide well maybe it wasn't a divorce let's stay married.
No, she might be divorced and now he can't stay married because
then it's a problem of a Gerusha גרושה. Gerusha. He can't remarry
her. So that's one Nafka Mina נפקא מינא. Nafka Mina. V'ee Erva
hi ואי ערווה היא V'ee Erva hi Tzarasah Ba'ee Chalitza צרתה בעיא
חליצה Tzarasah Ba'ee Chalitza and the other Nafka Mina נפקא מינא Nafka
Mina the Gemara גמרא Gemara gives, now it should be noted this
is not the Mishnah משנה, Mishnah, this is what the Gemara גמרא
Gemara in Gittin גיטין Gittin says is the implications of a Safek
Gierushin ספק גירושין. Safek Gierushin. V'ee Erva hi ואי ערווה היא V'ee
Erva hi then her co-wife is a questionable Tzarat Erva צרת ערווה
Tzarat Erva and therefore would not be able to walk off because
the woman might be Megureshet מגורשת Megureshet and therefore the co-wife is
obligated in Yibum יבום. Yibum. You can't do Yibum יבום Yibum because
she might be Eina Megureshet אינה מגורשת Eina Megureshet and a Tzarat
Erva צרת ערווה, Tzarat Erva, so what do you do? Ba'ee Chalitza
בעיא חליצה, Ba'ee Chalitza, you need Chalitza חליצה. Chalitza. So the Gemara
גמרא Gemara says look, in another Gemara גמרא Gemara it's interesting, you
know sort of self-referential because it's not really a question from a
Tannaic תנא Tannaic source, but in another Gemara גמרא Gemara we say
that a genuine Safek Gierushin ספק גירושין Safek Gierushin the Halacha הלכה
Halacha is Chalitza No Yibum חליצה Chalitza יבום, Yibum, not that she
just keeps her Chazaka חזקה Chazaka and she just walks off. V'lo
Amrinan ולא אמרינן V'lo Amrinan and we don't say she-mata omer choletzes
misyabemes שמא תאמר חולצת מתייבמת she-mata omer choletzes misyabemes that we're afraid
of being Machmir מחמיר Machmir and demanding Chalitza חליצה Chalitza because that
will lead to Yibum יבום. Yibum. No we don't say that, we
say let's demand Chalitza חליצה Chalitza in that case. Okay,
so the Gemara גמרא Gemara says so you see that in a
real Safek Gierushin ספק גירושין Safek Gierushin we are okay with demanding
Chalitza חליצה. Chalitza. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says Ha-itmar alah איתמר
עלה, Ha-itmar alah, no it was said about that, Rabbah v'Rav Yosef
d'amri tarvaihu רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרוייהו, Rabbah v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu,
Rabbah and Rav Yosef both said Hacha b'shtei kitei edim askinan הכא
בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן, Hacha b'shtei kitei edim askinan, we're actually talking
about two pairs of witnesses. Achas omeret karov la v'achas omeret karov
lo אחת אומרת קרוב לה ואחת אומרת קרוב לו. Achas omeret karov
la v'achas omeret karov lo. The reason there that she does not
retain her Chazaka חזקה, Chazaka, the woman who received the Get גט
Get and her Chazaka חזקה Chazaka of being married and the co-wife
her Chazaka חזקה Chazaka of being a Tzarat Erva צרת ערווה, Tzarat
Erva, the reason it doesn't retain her Chazaka חזקה Chazaka and then
just walk off without anything is because there is something that opposes
the Chazaka חזקה. Chazaka. It's not just a doubt, it's not just
an abstract doubt: oh we don't know where the Get גט Get
fell, then the Halacha הלכה Halacha is you retain your Chazaka חזקה
Chazaka and you assume that she remains married. But here there is
direct testimony against the Chazaka חזקה. Chazaka. The only thing is it's
contradicted testimony. Hacha b'shtei kitei edim askinan הכא בשתי כיתי עדים עסקינן,
Hacha b'shtei kitei edim askinan, we're talking about two pairs of witnesses.
two pairs of witnesses. אחת אומרת קרוב לה ואחת אומרת קרוב לו.
akhas omeres karov lah v'akhas omeres karov lo. One group of witnesses
says we definitely saw it and it was closer to her, and
the other one says we definitely saw it and it was closer
to him. So the rabbi said let's go to the instant replay
tape. So no, that was the problem.
Okay. דהוה ליה ספקא דאורייתא. dahavei leh sefeika d'oraisa. So that's a
biblical ספק. safek. Now what that means is that it creates a
ספק safek situation even in the face of a חזקה. chazakah. חזקה
chazakah means status quo. So if you have an abstract doubt, oh,
we don't know what happened, okay, keep things the status quo. But
if you have concrete testimony, even though it's contradictory testimony, which is
interesting, that pushes the חזקה chazakah aside and now you're really in
the world of doubt. So in that type of a case it's
a real דאורייתא d'oraisa doubt. It's not a דרבנן d'rabbanan חומרא. chumra.
It's a real דאורייתא d'oraisa ספק safek and therefore no more חזקה.
chazakah. And therefore all we can say is חליצה נעביד בה. chalitza
na'avid bah.
So therefore that's the case that
okay.
דהוה ליה ספקא דאורייתא. dahavei leh sefeika d'oraisa. ומתניתין דהכא, u'masnisin d'haka,
but here we're not talking about witnesses. ומתניתין דהכא בכת אחת, u'masnisin
d'haka be'chas akhas, so that it was one pair of witnesses that
were split. One guy said close to him, one guy said close
to her. Meaning here we won't the case we're talking when we're
talking about ספקות sfekos here it's not about two contradictory pairs of
witnesses. דהוה ליה ספקא דרבנן, dahavei leh sefeika d'rabbanan, so at most
it would be a rabbinic ספק. safek. Meaning דאורייתא d'oraisa you would
go by the status quo. Okay. So that's the גמרא's Gemara answer.
Why did our משנה mishnah not talk about ספק? safek? Because here
we're talking about cases where it's just a who knows what happened.
So the real דאורייתא d'oraisa הלכה halakhah is you rely on the
status quo and in that case you wouldn't even demand a חליצה.
chalitza. How about the fact that we say in the משנה mishnah
over in גיטין Gittin that even though there's a status quo you
demand חליצה? chalitza? That's cause there's testimony against the status quo. Even
though it's contradictory testimony, that's enough to create a real ספק. safek.
Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this. וממאי דמתניתין דהכא
בכת אחת? u'mima'i d'masnisin d'haka be'chas akhas? What makes you say that
our משנה mishnah should be limited to talking when for example it
talks about קידושין kiddushin and it says there's a ספק קידושין? safek
kiddushin? What makes you say that we're limited to talking about like
a split testimony, one witness says one, the other, meaning what I'll
call an abstract doubt and not direct testimony against? How do you
know? Maybe our משנה mishnah is talking about even cases of direct
testimony? דומיא דקידושין. dumya d'kiddushin. No, because the case of קידושין kiddushin
is not direct testimony, two witnesses against two witnesses. מה קידושין בכת
אחת אף גירושין בכת אחת. mah kiddushin be'chas akhas af girushin be'chas
akhas. The same way the case of קידושין kiddushin it's like one
pair of two witnesses split, one says one, one says the other,
so it's not two witnesses saying directly testifying against the status quo,
the same is true by גירושין. girushin. Of course that just begs
the question. וקידושין גופייהו? v'kiddushin gufeihu? And how do you know the
case of קידושין kiddushin where the משנה mishnah speaks about like you
don't know whether the ring was thrown closer to her or closer
to him? ממאי דבכת אחת? mima'i d'be'chas akhas? How do you know
it's like one split pair? Meaning how do you know it's like
just a question of duh we don't know what happened? דילמא בשתי
כיתי עדים? dilma b'shtei kitei edim? Maybe the cases that we're talking
about even in the קידושין kiddushin are contradictory witnesses and therefore apply
to the גירושין girushin would undermine the חזקה? chazakah? So the גמרא
Gemara says no. אי בשתי כיתי עדים, i b'shtei kitei edim, if
it was about two pairs of
witnesses. תתייבם ואין בכך כלום? tisyabem v'ein b'kach klum? How could you
have suggested earlier now this is a little bit of a problem,
Rashi and Tosafot discuss it because it's like self-referential.
Okay, it doesn't really prove it based on the משנה, mishnah, it
really proves based on the presumption that we had before. But I'm
not going to try to solve that problem, I'll just read the
גמרא Gemara the simple way. If it was talking about two contradictory
pairs of witnesses, how could you say before when we said do
a חליצה chalitza in the case of ספק קידושין safek kiddushin that
we wouldn't care if that חליצה chalitza led to a יבום? yibbum?
Okay, how could you have said that? תתייבם ואין בכך כלום קיימי
עדים דקאמרי קרוב לה? tisyabem v'ein b'kach klum kaimi edim d'ka'amri karov
lah? There's witnesses that say that the money was really close to
her and therefore she really is married and really the co-wife is
a צרת ערווה. tzaras ervah. And you're going to say we're not
going to be afraid that he might come to do a יבום?
yibbum? ואת אמרת תתייבם ואין בכך כלום? v'at amart tisyabem v'ein b'kach
klum? So how could you have said that? Of course that again,
the problem is that it's self-referential.
Before we thought you went by the חזקה. chazakah. If you went
by the חזקה, chazakah, then the woman would be presumed to be
not married in the case of ספק קידושין, safek kiddushin, the co-wife
would be presumed to be eligible for יבום yibbum and we could
say we're not afraid that it'll lead to יבום yibbum because we
go by חזקה. chazakah. Now we're saying how do you know that
the case isn't when there're contradictory witnesses and you throw out the
חזקה? chazakah? In that case we couldn't have said that we weren't
afraid that you would do יבום. yibbum. But maybe that's exactly the
point, maybe you were wrong before. All right. So Rashi and Tosafot
try to figure that out. Anyway we're not going to worry about
that. Okay. ותו, v'su, says the גמרא. Gemara. So anyway we have
a possibility which we is a reasonable argument in the משנה mishnah
that when you have two contradictory pairs of witnesses it undermines the
חזקה chazakah and then it really would have allowed for a genuine
case of a ספק. safek. We know by גיטין Gittin that we
say that in מסכת גיטין. Masechet Gittin. So why did our משנה
mishnah not have that possibility by the גט get in our משנה
mishnah of two contradictory pairs of witnesses? So one argument is somehow
we know that's not what the משנה mishnah is talking about. Let's
see now what the גמרא Gemara says. ותו v'su and the גמרא
Gemara says anyway, moreover, beyond all of this. And two in שתי
כיתי
עדים נמי סבירא דרבנן היא, shti kitei edim nami s'veira d'rabbanan hee,
you're wrong! In two cases of contradictory witnesses, because they contradict one
another, we don't say, oh, there's witnesses against the חזקת דאורייתא, chazakas
d'oraisha, the חזקה. chazaka. We say there's contradictory testimony, throw out all
the testimony and you're back to the חזקה. chazaka. So here's a
great question. What is the הלכה? halacha? If you have a חזקה
chazaka and a ספק, safek, you go by the חזקה. chazaka. Okay,
you don't know what to do, you go by the status quo.
If there's a חזקה chazaka against witnesses, you go by the witnesses.
If there's חזקה chazaka against witnesses, but there's contradictory witnesses, so do
you say, well, once there's direct testimony even if it winds up
being contradict, that's enough to undermine the חזקה chazaka and then you're
left with a blank slate and a ספק, safek, or do you
say, throw out both pairs of witnesses, they contradict one another and
you're back to the חזקה? chazaka? So that's what I think we
all would say. Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
say now. Before the גמרא Gemara said the חזקה chazaka becomes neutralized,
now the גמרא Gemara is going to say that's not true, you
actually do go back to the חזקה. chazaka. So let's take a
look. Okay, דהא אמרינן אוקי תרי לבהדי תרי ואוקמה איתתא אחזקה, de-ha
amrinan okei trei l'bahadi trei v'okmah it-ta a-chazakah, put two against two
and have the woman retain her חזקה. chazaka. Now how do you
know you should say that at least at a דאורייתא d'oraisha level?
מידי דהוה אנכסי דבר שטיא, meidi de-hava a-nichsei d'bar shatya, like the
story about the property of this person called בר שטיא. Bar Shatya.
Now בר שטיא Bar Shatya seems to maybe be a name but
also as we're going to see he was somebody that was, no,
he was somebody that might not have always been sane, a שוטה.
shoteh. Yeah, a שוטה. shoteh. So the question was, so he was
somebody, you know, maybe had episodes, psychotic breaks, and the question was
when he engaged in certain business transactions, was he of right mind
or not of right mind? So what was the story? דבר שטיא
זבין נכסי, de-Bar Shatya zavin nichsei, he sold some property. אתו בי
תרי ואמרי כשהוא חלים זבין, ato bei trei v'amri k'she-hu chalim zavin,
two witnesses came and they say he sold it when he was
of right mind. ואתו בי תרי ואמרי כשהוא שוטה זבין, v'ato bei
trei v'amri k'she-hu shoteh zavin, and then another two witnesses came and
said no
he sold it when he was not of right mind. So what
do you do? ואמר רב אשי אוקי תרי לבהדי תרי וארעא אוקמה
בחזקת בר שטיא, v'amar Rav Ashi okei trei l'bahadi trei v'ara okmah
b'chazakas Bar Shatya, put two against two, throw them all out, okay,
because they contradict, so you wipe the slate, so you basically just
reject all of
that, and have the property be assumed still under the control of
בר שטיא, Bar Shatya, that was its default position. Now there's what
to be talked about about the difference between a חזקה chazaka when
it means ownership of property as opposed to you know who was
the previous owner, who was the owner until this point, as opposed
to a sense of a חזקה chazaka about a status quo of
a person, but we're not going to worry about that right now.
You could but here at least what you say is, if it
were a real ספק, safek, why don't we say something else, I
don't know, split it? You know if there's a real ספק safek
who owns property, that's like the first משנה בבא מציעא. Mishnah Bava
Metzia. Okay, but no, we say we don't know, we throw out
all the witnesses and we go back to the status quo. So
you see that's the real הלכה. halacha. So therefore we're back to
the point. How do we say in a case of גט, get,
we know that there's a משנה Mishnah in גיטין Gittin that we
say basically is that when there's a ספק, safek, a real ספק
גט, safek get, you do חליצה? chalitzah? And now we're saying you
can't distinguish any case, whether it's contradictory witnesses, whether it's an abstract
doubt, the דאורייתא d'oraisha should be status quo and not need חליצה.
chalitzah. So if you still need חליצה, chalitzah, it means we're going
to be מחמיר machmir in that case of ספק גט, safek get,
even though in principle you could go by חזקה. chazaka. Now if
that's true, why did our משנה Mishnah not give a classic ספק
גט? safek get? If the הלכה halacha is that yes, in principle
go by חזקה chazaka but nevertheless play it safe and demand חליצה,
chalitzah, if that's really the הלכה halacha like we say over there
in the משנה Mishnah in גיטין, Gittin, why did we not have
that scenario here? So let's take a look. Now the גמרא Gemara
switches gears. אלא אמר אביי, ella amar Abaye, so therefore Abaye says,
יגיד עליו רעו, yagid alav rei'o, quoting a פסוק pasuk in איוב,
Iyov, let his friend, his friend will tell on him, will sort
of reveal about him. So let's figure it out by the context
and the juxtaposition of the משנה. Mishnah. תנא בקידושין והוא הדין לגירושין.
tana b'kiddushin v'hu ha-din l'gerushin. So you know what? As opposed to
emphasizing the fact that the משנה Mishnah gave a different scenario by
גט get to say that the case by קידושין kiddushin isn't relevant,
no, we're saying actually you learn one out from the other. By
קידושין kiddushin it gives a classic case of a ספק safek that
you threw it and you didn't know who it was close to
and that has a הלכה halacha of חליצה chalitzah not יבום. yibbum.
So by גט get also the same would be true if it
was a classic case of a ספק, safek, same הלכה. halacha. Why
did it give a different case by גט? get? To give you
an additional scenario,
not to exclude the example by קידושין kiddushin to give you another
example by גט. get. Okay, תנא בגירושין, tana b'gerushin, the question of
a real
ספק, safek, והוא הדין לקידושין. v'hu ha-din l'kiddushin. So
then it gave an example by גט get which wasn't a real
ספק, safek, it was a גט פסול, get pasul, והוא הדין לקידושין,
v'hu ha-din l'kiddushin, and the same would be true if you had
a קידושין kiddushin that were רבנן פסול. rabbanan pasul. So the point
is, do not read these scenarios in the משנה Mishnah as mutually
exclusive. Actually by קידושין kiddushin it gave one. Actually by קידושין Kiddushin?
*kiddushin* it gave one set of examples, by גירושין Geirushin. *gerushin* it
gave another set of examples, but they're both true by the other
cases as well. Okay, and now we have come to the conclusion,
רבא Rava *Rava* will nuance that a little bit, but basically the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* in terms of the earlier discussion has come to
the conclusion that even though in principle you're right, that when even
when there's an abstract ספק *safek* and even when there's contradictory witnesses,
the principle דאורייתא de'oraisa *de-Oraita* is you go to the חזקה *chazaka*,
and therefore in the case of ספק גט get, *safek get*, the
ערווה *erva* should be בחזקת אשת איש *be-chezkat eshet ish* and the
צרה *tzara* should be צרת ערווה *tzarat erva* and she should walk
away without anything, still at a rabbinic level we're going to be
מחמיר *machmir* and demand a חליצה chalitzah *chalitza*. Okay, even though there's
costs to that חומרא *chumra* like we heard about yesterday, and potential
downside, we're going to be מחמיר *machmir*. And yes, you're right, the
same would be true by גט get *get*. The משנה mishnah. *Mishna*
didn't say it, but it's also true by גט get? *get*. Okay.
אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, that's what אביי *Abaye* says. אמר
ליה רבא Rava *Amar lei Rava*, רבא *Rava* says back to him,
יגיד עליו רעו *Yagid alav re'o*, if you can learn out one
case from the other, מאי זהו דקתני *mai zehu de-katani*, why does
it say, "This is the case of ספק קידושין kiddushin, *safek kiddushin*,"
"This is the case of ספק גירושין *safek gerushin*"? That sounds like
we're being very precise. We're not just giving, "Here's one or two
examples here and one or two examples here." It says like, "this
is the case," like it doesn't apply in the other direction. אלא
Ella, אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Ella amar Rava*, so here's what רבא
*Rava* says. כל שיש בקידושין יש בגירושין *Kol she-yesh be-kiddushin yesh be-gerushin*.
You're right. One of them is לאו דווקא *lav davka*. The cases
by קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* are classic ספק *safek*. You don't know if
it got close to him or close to her or whatever. That
would be true to a גט get? *get* too. Any classic ספק
*safek* would be true in both scenarios. Okay? But the case by
גט get? *get* wouldn't be true by the case by קידושין kiddushin
*kiddushin*. But ויש בגירושין *ve-yesh be-gerushin*, there are cases in this משנה
mishnah *Mishna* that apply to גט get. *get* like all the פסולים
*psulim* of the גט get. *get*—you didn't have the זמן zman *zman*,
you didn't have two עדים eidim *edim*—מה שאין בקידושין *ma she-ein be-kiddushin*,
that don't apply in the קידושין kiddushin. *kiddushin* scenario. וזהו vezehu, דגירושין
לאו דווקא *Ve-zehu de-gerushin lav davka*, when it says that these are
the cases... זהו ספק
גירושין *Zehu safek gerushin*. Oh, when it says, "this is the case
of גירושין *gerushin*," it doesn't mean "this" to exclude others. Other things
also are true by גירושין *gerushin*, not just the פסול psul גט
get, *pasul get*, but a real ספק *safek*. So that was לאו
דווקא *lav davka*. Okay. However, זהו דקידושין *zehu de-kiddushin*, when it says,
"these are the cases of פסול psul קידושין kiddushin *pasul kiddushin*," that...
אלא Ella, משום דתני *ella mishum de-tani*. Oh, I'm sorry, I skipped
a line. Thank you. זהו דקידושין לאו דווקא אלא משום דתני זהו
בקידושין *Zehu de-kiddushin lav davka ella mishum de-tani zehu be-kiddushin*. The only
reason it says these are the cases of גירושין *gerushin* is not,
doesn't mean to exclude the class, it doesn't mean to exclude, it
would... גירושין *gerushin* is not limited. The case of גירושין *gerushin* also
includes classic ספק *safek*. It only said that because it's saying the
word זהו *zehu* by קידושין kiddushin, *kiddushin*. תני נמי זהו בגירושין *Tani
nami zehu be-gerushin*. So that's why it said it by גירושין *gerushin*,
"these are the cases of ספק גט get *safek get*." But it's
really a bigger category; it really includes a classic ספק *safek*. וזהו
דקידושין *Ve-zehu de-kiddushin*, but when it says, "these are the cases of
ספק קידושין kiddushin *safek kiddushin*," למעוטי מאי *le-ma'utei mai*, what's that excluding?
It's excluding the פסולי גט get. *psulei get*. The פסולי גט get,
*psulei get* would not apply to קידושין *kiddushin*. למעוטי זמן zman. דליתא
בקידושין *Le-ma'utei zman de-leita be-kiddushin*, to include the case of the פסולי
גט get, *psulei get* that doesn't apply by קידושין *kiddushin*. So you
remember basically, right, the לישנא *lishna*... Right,
the משנה mishnah. *Mishna* says, right, by קידושין *kiddushin*, it said basically,
ספק קרוב לו קרוב לה *safek karov lo karov lah*, ספק קרוב
לו *safek karov lo*. ספק קרוב לו *Safek karov lo*. Right? That
was the cases of זהו *zehu*, you know, ספק קידושין *safek kiddushin*,
whatever. Okay?
That's what the משנה Mishna *Mishna* said. By גירושין *gerushin* it said,
right, you know, כתב בכתב ידו *katav bi-chtav yado*, you know, בכתב
ידו ואין עליו עדים *bi-chtav yado ve-ein alav edim*, עדים
*edim*, then it had a case of אין בו זמן ein bo
zeman *ein bo zman*, and then it had a case of עד
אחד Eid echad *ed echad*. Okay. And then it says, זהו ספק
גירושין *zehu safek gerushin*. Okay? So the point is, what was bothering
us is what about the classic ספק *safek* by גירושין *gerushin*? So
we spent yesterday saying, "Oh, in that case the הלכה halacha. *halacha*
would be different because you would go by the חזקה *chazaka* and
you wouldn't even be מחמיר *machmir* for a חליצה chalitzah *chalitza*." Now
we said, "No, it's not true. It is true you would go
by the חזקה דאורייתא d'oraisa *chazaka de-Oraita*, but it's also true that
forget about the דאורייתא d'oraisa *de-Oraita*, דרבנן derabanan *de-rabbanan* we're going to
demand a חליצה chalitzah *chalitza* and the same הלכה halacha. *halacha* would
apply." So if the same הלכה *halacha* would apply, what's the זהו
*zehu* that seems to say only this? So what רבא *Rava* says
is, this זהו *zehu* is really לאו דווקא *lav davka*. This case
of גירושין *gerushin* is a bigger category. This would also be true
here, you would demand a חליצה chalitzah *chalitza*. But the זהו *zehu*
here is דווקא *davka*, because the cases of קידושין *kiddushin* don't include
the cases of גירושין *gerushin*. If you had a scenario like this...
Now, by the way, where are you getting a scenario about a
written document by קידושין *kiddushin*? Because we'd be talking about קידושי שטר
shtar *kiddushei shtar*, not about קידושי... that wouldn't be about קידושין *kiddushin*,
we're talking about קידושי שטר shtar. *kiddushei shtar*, not about קידושי כסף
kiddushei kesef, *kiddushei kesef*. So if you had a קידושי שטר shtar.
*kiddushei shtar* that was written with these problems, it would not be
the same issue by קידושין *kiddushin*. קידושין *Kiddushin* is limited to these
ספקות *sfekot*, these problems which are not really ספקות *sfekot*, which are
פסולי דרבנן derabanan, *psulei de-rabbanan*, don't apply to
קידושין *kiddushin*. Okay. Some of them actually would, but not all of
them would apply to קידושין. Let's take a look. So, וזהו דקידושין
תנא להו, Vezehu d'Kiddushin tana lehu, וזהו דקידושין למיעוטי מאי? Vezehu d'Kiddushin
l'miutei mai?
Which cases is it excluding that would not be relevant to קידושין?
למיעוטי זמן, L'miutei zman, דליכא בקידושין, d'leika b'Kiddushin, that the lack of
זמן zeman would not make a פסול pasul, שטר קידושין. shtar Kiddushin.
The lack of two עדים would, the lack of, even if it
was written in his handwriting, עד אחד would, that would be a
פסול pasul שטר קידושין, shtar Kiddushin, that would have the same הלכה.
But one of these, this one, is only relevant by גירושין. The
case of not having a date, that פוסל posel a גט, get.
but it would not פוסל posel a שטר קידושין. shtar Kiddushin. And
that's why we said וזהו, not to exclude this from down here,
but to exclude this problem of lacking a date, that wouldn't be
a problem by a שטר קידושין. shtar Kiddushin. And now we're just
going to focus on why that's true. Why is the lack of
a date in the document a problem by a גט get, and
not a problem by a שטר קידושין? shtar Kiddushin? So let's take
a look. ומפני מה לא תיקנו זמן בקידושין? U-mipnei mah lo tiknu
zman b'Kiddushin? Why did they not demand for a date in a
שטר קידושין? shtar Kiddushin? The Rabbis? And then say that it would
be rabbinically invalid without it. So, הניחא למאן דאמר משום פירי. Hani'cha
l'man d'amar mishum peiri. ארוסה לית לה פירי. Arusa leit lah peiri.
So there's a question, why did they demand a date in a
גט? get Why do you need a date in a גט? get
So what's the most obvious reason why you need a date in
a גט? get
So you know when she's divorced. So, well, okay, what do you
mean? But I mean if she wants to get remarried she'll take
out her גט. get. Who needs a date? Anytime she takes it
out. What?
Exactly, so you'll know maybe there was some activity in the past,
what exactly the story was. So that's the easiest explanation. The way
the גמרא Gemara frames that is שמא יחפה על בת אחותו. Shema
yachapeh al bas achoso. Maybe he'll try to protect his niece. Meaning,
imagine that if a man is divorcing his wife he wouldn't really
care about her unless she was anyway related to him from a
different direction, so maybe he had married his niece. So anyway, but
the basic point being maybe he's trying to protect his wife. So
even though he's divorcing her, let's say she committed adultery and he's
divorcing her, but nevertheless he wants to protect her. So what he's
going to do is he's going to predate a גט. get So
she can basically say that she was divorced before
this act of adultery occurred, at least save her from getting executed
by the court. Okay, so that's one explanation. What?
She's pregnant. Yeah, or say the kid from being a ממזר. mamzer.
What? Right, exactly. So the other possibility is much more mundane, which
is that from the moment a woman is divorced,
then
the husband is no longer entitled to eat the, what's it called,
usufruct, to eat the פירות נכסי מלוג, peiros nichsei melog, to eat
the fruit that grows from the woman's property. Okay, so, okay, so
then he would have no, so what would be the issue? If
you don't date it, then he's more entitled to keep on taking
the fruit. So the concern is the following. Look at רש"י. Rashi.
רש"י Rashi explains it. So it says, בגיטין, B'Gittin,
הניחא למאן דאמר, Hani'cha l'man d'amar, it's the third line down in
the narrow
lines, בגיטין בפרק כל הגט מפני מה תיקנו חכמים זמן בגיט משום
פירי, B'Gittin b'perek Kol HaGet mipnei mah tiknu chachamim zman b'get mishum
peiri, לדעת מאימתי תגבה מבעלה פירות שאכל מנכסי מלוג שלה. Lada'as mei'eimasai
tigbeh mi-ba'alah peiros she-achal mi-nichsei melog shelah. So basically, when can she
collect from her husband, excuse me,
מבעלה פירות שאכל מנכסי מלוג, mi-ba'alah peiros she-achal mi-nichsei melog, when can
she collect the fruit that he's eating from her stuff from the
moment she's divorced? So we have to have proof when she's divorced.
Now that should be in the husband's self-interest to write the זמן.
zeman, Because דקסבר משעה שנתן עיניו בה לגרשה שוב אין לבעל פירות.
d'kasvar mi-sha'ah she-nasan einav bah l'garshah shuv ein l'ba'al peiros. So the
question of course is maybe he signed, he wrote the date on
the גט, get right, maybe he wrote the date on the גט
get before he actually gave her the גט. get It doesn't matter.
From the time you're writing the גט, get you forfeit the right
to the benefit from the fruit. Okay, so therefore it's in the
husband's interest right,
not to put the date on the גט, get, right? It's in
the husband's interest not to put the date on the גט. get
Oh, I'm sorry, so here's the problem. I'm sorry, I misstated before.
Let's go back for a second to the case about trying to
protect his wife from a charge of adultery. So once we demand
a date on a גט, get we're not concerned about predating, because
witnesses have to sign it. Okay, so we're not concerned about actually
forging the date. Witnesses won't sign it if it's false. But we
demand a date because if we didn't demand a גט get date,
you'd give your wife a גט get without a date and she
would claim that it was from before the act of adultery. Once
we demand a date, we're not afraid of predating. The witnesses will
ensure that won't happen. Similarly here. So that's why we demand a
date. Similarly here. You'll write a גט get for your wife and
not date it. Why? So that anytime she says look I'm divorced,
you have to give me the fruit that you took from my
property, he says no I just divorced you yesterday. It hasn't been
five years, it was yesterday. So once we demand that it be
dated, then it'll be the right date and then the woman will
be can get her fruit from the time that she's entitled. Okay,
so those are the two reasons, משום פירי mishum peiri and what
the גמרא Gemara calls משום בת אחותו. mishum bas achoso.
How do you translate the word מלוג melog in that?
I'm not going to talk, we'll talk about that when we get
to it later. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara, says like this. Okay,
so ומפני מה לא תיקנו זמן בקידושין? U'mipnei mah lo tiknu zeman
b'kiddushin? הניחא למאן דאמר משום פירי. Hani'acha l'man d'amar mishum peiri. If
the reason for the date is to make sure the woman gets
back the fruit from her property that she's entitled to and the
husband doesn't claim I just divorced you yesterday, so ארוסה לית לה
פירי. arusa leit lah peiri. So there's no purpose of putting out
the date in the שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin because the husband isn't
entitled to the fruit from the time of קידושין, he's only entitled
to it from the time of נישואין. nissu'in. So why do you
need the date? Right? No ownership of property switches at the time
of קידושין. So if the focus is—so but doesn't matter, it's not
relevant for the question of ownership of property. So if the reason
of the date is to ensure proper ownership of property, it's not
relevant for שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin. So then we understand why it's
not a problem not to have a date. אלא, says the גמרא,
Gemara that's fine. אלא למאן דאמר משום בת אחותו, Ella l'man d'amar
mishum bat achoto,
if the problem, if the need for the date is to ensure
that you know somebody doesn't cover up an act of adultery, you
know exactly when she was divorced, so ליתקין זמן? litkin zeman? So
the same thing should demand that we have a date in the
שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin so that you know when she was married
and when she wasn't married. So if there are questions similarly there
about adultery or whatever, you know, what will happen? You give her—I
mean, you give her a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin without a date,
then she commits adultery and then she claims no I just got
married yesterday after that act with that other man. Okay, so we
should—if we're concerned about that, we should similarly be concerned that we
have accurate information about that. אלא, so that's the גמרא's Gemara question.
So the answer is משום דאיכא דמקדש בכספא ואיכא דמקדש בשטרא לא
תיקנו רבנן זמן. mishum d'ika d'mikadesh b'chaspa v'ika d'mikadesh b'shtara lo tiknu
rabanan zeman. The גמרא Gemara says look, often enough we're not going
to have precise knowledge about when she got married anyway because people
marry with money much more often than with a שטר קידושין. shtar
kiddushin. I once had a couple that came and asked me, they
said we want to do קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. I said excuse
me? Anyway, so I did some research, it was quite fascinating, and
even though there's like almost no גמרא Gemara on it, like three
lines of גמרא Gemara discussion on it, there are no cases in
the גמרא Gemara about it. There's all these cases about קידושי כסף,
kiddushei kesef, no cases of קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. I contacted מרדכי
פרידמן, Mordechai Friedman, Friedman? Freedman.
Friedman, who did all the work with the קהיר גניזה Cairo Geniza
and all of the כתובות ketubot and all of the stuff about
marriages and he says in all of that evidence he says we
have not one instance of קידושי שטרא. kiddushei shtara. So I said,
I don't think there's absolutely any מסורה massorah about this, I'm not
doing any קידושי שטרא kiddushei shtara with you guys. Anyway, so
but the גמרא Gemara so it's funny the גמרא Gemara says some
people do it this way, some people do it that way. The
evidence is everybody does קידושי כסף, kiddushei kesef, nobody does קידושי שטרא.
kiddushei shtara. Anyway, the point is often enough if not the vast
majority of times, there's no concrete evidence of what the date of
קידושין was anyway. And since it's not happening by כסף קידושין, kesef
kiddushin, we're not going to go ahead and all of a sudden
you decide to do בשטרא b'shtara all of a sudden now we're
going to be worried about knowing the date. You're not worried about
knowing the date when it's קידושי כסף, kesef. so we're not going
to make a sense to invalidate a שטר shtar. and require it
all of a sudden because you're doing it with a שטר.
Okay, דאיכא דקני בכספא ואיכא דקני בשטרא ולא תיקנו רבנן זמן. d'ika
d'kani b'chaspa v'ika d'kani b'shtara lo tiknu rabanan zeman. Okay. אמר ליה
רב אחא בריה דרב יוסף לרב אשי, Amar lei Rav Acha brei
d'Rav Yosef l'Rav Ashi, והא עבדא v'ha avda but slave דאיכא דקני
בכספא ואיכא בשטרא, d'ika d'kani b'chaspa v'ika b'shtara, some people buy slaves
with money and some with documents, ותיקנו רבנן זמן, v'tiknu rabanan zeman,
and the rabbis demanded that there be a date in that document.
Why we don't have to worry about? But the point is even
though you don't always do it with a שטר. So the גמרא
Gemara says no. התם רובא
בשטרא, Hatam ruba b'shtara,
which makes sense, obviously people want
a document
to prove ownership of their slaves, right? It's a property and they
want it documented. So therefore we're going to demand זמן and we
won't worry about the exceptions when it's done with כסף. kesef, הכא
רובא בכסף. Hacha ruba b'chesef. And now the גמרא Gemara. says out
here, the majority, the vast majority is with כסף, kesef we're not
going to all of a sudden say when you switch gears and
do זמן, now we're going to get worried about having it dated.
Okay, so that's one answer. So that's why this case here, these
problems are not all problems by קידושין. The אין בו זמן is
only a גיטין gittin problem. איבעית אימא, Iba'it eima, yeah?
What
about the כתובה? ketubah?
Isn't that always given?
No, כתובה ketubah is given at the נישואין, nissu'in, which often would—yeah,
which often would be a good deal afterwards. איבעית אימא משום דלא
אפשר. Iba'it eima mishum d'lo efshar. Or here's another reason why we
don't have the date in it in a שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin.
Because it's not possible. Meaning, it's possible but it wouldn't do any
good. Why wouldn't it do any good? היכי נעביד? Heichi ne'avid? What
do you want to do with this שטר קידושין? shtar kiddushin? לנחהו
גבי דידה? lenacheihu gabi didah? Have her hold onto the שטר קידושין?
shtar kiddushin? מחקה ליה. machkah lei. So so what? The whole reason
to have a date is so that we can prove when she
committed adultery. So if you don't have the date, then she can
always say that she got married later. So guess what? She's not
the right person to be holding onto the שטר. Okay, erase it
or whoops I can't seem to find my שטר קידושין. shtar kiddushin.
So that's not going to do any good. Or hold onto the
שטר קידושין *shetar kiddushin*, מחקה ליה *machalei*. So say okay, after you
give your wife a שטר קידושין *shetar kiddushin*, you hold onto the
שטר *shetar*. So זימנין דבת אחותו היא *zimnin de-bat achoto hee*, מחפי
לה *mechaplei lah*. Same problem. Maybe he'll want to protect her. He
is similar case of a niece, same way he'll protect her with
a גט get *get*. Whoops, can't find the שטר קידושין *shetar kiddushin*.
Okay, לנתחה גבי עדים *lincha gabei edim*. Have the witness, have like
some third party, the witnesses who witnessed the שטר *shetar* hold onto
it. אי דזיכירי *ee de-zechiri*, look, that won't help you. If anyway
they remember what they you know you know the date that they
saw the קידושין *kiddushin*, ליתו ליתסן *leisu lisan*, they'll come and testify
on their own. ואי לא *ve-ee lo*, and if they don't remember,
זימנין דחזו *zimnin de-chazu*, look at the שטר *shetar*, זימנין דחזו מכתבא
*zimnin de-chazu miksava*, ואתו מסהדי *ve-asu mesahadi*, they'll look at the at
the שטר *shetar* and they'll come and they'll testify
based on what they read in the document, not based on their
actual memory. ורחמנא אמר v'rachmana amar, *ve-rachmana amar*, מפיכם ולא מכתבם *mi-pihem
velo miksavam*, and you can only testify based on what you remember,
you can't testify based on something you wrote down.
So the גמרא Gemara. *Gemara*, so therefore, it's not going to do
any good. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, אי הכי *ee hachi*,
בגירושין נמי *be-geirusin nami*. So by a גט get *get* also won't
do any good to have the זמן *zman*. Okay, because people will
just get rid of it or erase it. Of course there's an
obvious answer. By a גט get *get*, she's assumed to be מקודשת
*mekudeshet*. She needs to produce the גט get *get* to get her
off. So there's no way the גט get. *get* can whoops be
lost. Okay, נימא הכי *neima hachi*, no, התם לאצולה דידה קאתי *hasam
le-atzolah didah ka-asei*, there you need to produce the גט get *get*
to protect her. So הכא לחובה דידה קאתי *hacha le-chovah didah ka-asei*,
here the existence of the שטר *shetar* is a detriment, so you'll
lose the שטר *shetar*. Okay, same problem. I mean the, now, I
don't know, the בית דין beit din *Beit Din*, still the idea
is similar to the concern by the עדים *edim* and so on.
The בית דין beit din *Beit Din* can't testify מתוך הכתב *mitok
ha-ksav*. Now I want to say something very briefly, it's a fascinating
issue מפיכם ולא מפי כתבם *mi-pihem velo mi-pi ksavm*, given the time
we can't really explore further but I just want to say two
important points about it. Number one is, תוספות tosafos *Tosafot* says, I
don't understand. The whole point about signing a שטר *shetar* is that
the document testified can be produced as evidence. So what do you
mean the witnesses will read it and testify and they won't have
remembered it? Don't read it, don't testify, just come and deliver the
document to the court and let the signed document serve. And תוספות
tosafos *Tosafot* says, you know what, that's right, that would totally work.
But the problem is, we're afraid that they won't do that. They'll
read it and they'll say oh yeah, and then they'll come and
they'll say secondhand and they won't produce the document. But of course
if they actually would just produce the document and not say anything,
we would go by the document, that's the whole point about a
signed document. Point number one. Point number two is that not only
that, but actually if you use something to prompt your memory, forget
that it's a signed שטר *shetar*. You write a little note in
a diary, and you reread the diary and then you actually do
recall the events. Now of course we know that memory is completely
fallible and influenced by things that we other types of things, but
nevertheless the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* actually says that you're allowed to remind
your use those things to remind yourself if in the end you're
testifying based on what you remember, not based on what because you
saw it written there. You actually don't remember, but I'm saying it
happened because I saw it was written in my diary. That would
be invalid. But if it actually caused you to remember, that would
be valid. So the interesting thing about this scenario is that there's
two cases which would be fine. Just produce the document, or help
it remind you and then testify based on what you genuinely remember.
The only case that's not good is to testify about the event
that you don't remember and you're not producing the document, but you're
testifying it because you read it in the document. Okay, and that
would be the problematic case.
Okay, what's this that he just had handwritten notes and that would
serve
as
a memory jog but he might rely more on the written document,
right, that even though I don't remember I can testify because I
saw it written in the גט get. *get*. Exactly. Okay, so that's
exactly it. Now I'll read you also, see I said I wasn't
going to do it but I can't resist.
So it says, and if you take a look here, right, so
take a look at תוספות tosafos *Tosafot*, דחזו *de-chazu*, like three lines
before it gets wide, he says, ואומר ר''י דהכא נמי אם היו
מעידים שכך ראו בשטר *ve-omer Ri de-hacha nami im hayu me-idim she-kach
ra-u ba-shetar*, if they actually didn't just claim they remember when they
didn't, but they either produced the document or testified what they saw
in the document, שפיר הוו עבדי *shapir havu avdi*, that would work.
דהרי הם כאילו מעידים בעינו עדות שנתקבלה בבית דין *de-harei hem ke-ilu
me-idim be-inu edut she-nitkabela be-Veit Din*. דעדים החתומים אשטר נעשו כמי שנחקרה
עדותן בבית דין *de-edim ha-chasumim a-shetar na-asu ke-mi she-nechkerah edutan be-Veit Din*.
אבל חיישינן שמא לא יעידו שכך ראו בשטר *aval chashinan shema lo
ya-idu she-kach ra-u ba-shetar*, אלא שמא יעידו על המעשה עצמו כאילו הם
זוכרים ואינם זוכרים *ela shema ya-idu al ha-ma'aseh atzmo ke-ilu hem zochrim
ve-einam zochrim*, אלא על פי הכתב *ela al pi ha-ksav*. Okay, and
then the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, right, אלא וכן הא דאמרינן פרק
בזה בכתובות *ela ve-chein ha de-amrinan perek ba-zeh bi-Ktubot*, כותב אדם עדותו
על השטר ומעיד עליה אפילו אחר כמה שנים והוא שזוכר מעצמו *kotev
adam eduto al ha-shetar u-me'id aleha afilu achar kama shanim ve-hu she-zocher
me-atzmo*. אבל אין זוכר מעצמו לא *aval ein zocher me-atzmo lo*. התם
נמי לא איירי שבמה שכך ראה כתוב *hasam nami lo airi she-be-ma
she-kach ra'ah katuv*, אלא במעיד על המעשה עצמו *ela bi-me'id al ha-ma'aseh
atzmo*. Okay, so ועוד התם לא הוי שטר אלא שכתב לזכרון דברים
בעלמא *ve-od hasam lo havei shetar ela she-katav le-zikaron devarim be-alma*. Okay,
etc., etc. So therefore it says as well there that now again
there's a good question of what does it mean זוכרה מעצמו *zochreha
me-atzmo* as opposed to not זוכרה מעצמו *zochreha me-atzmo*, how much is
the שטר *shetar* serving as a prompt? And how much do you
genuinely really remember it? But again the primary issue is is that
you have to actually be testifying based on what you remembered. But
if you testify it was written in a signed document, that's okay.
The problem is when you testify that you remembered it and you
actually are not remembering it, but you're just getting that information elsewhere.
Okay, and I want to just read also one other line that
again I can't resist because this is a fascinating point about what's
it called, about a I'm forgetting the word for this when you
a deposition. So ואומר רי דשמא רבנו תם d'shema rabeinu tam שנהגו
עכשיו shenagu achshav the next line in תוספות ששולחים העדים עדותם בכתב
ידם לבית דין. shesholchim ha'edim edusam bechesav yadam l'beis din. They can
actually write out your testimony and send it. So that's different. That's
not your testifying on something written that you didn't actually witness or
you don't actually remember, but you're communicating your testimony through writing.
דלא קרינן ביה מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם d'lo karinan bei mipihem v'lo
mipi kesavam כיון דהם זוכרים עדותם keivan d'heim zochrim edusam since they
do remember, the form of communication is through writing, that's okay. Okay,
the problem is when you don't actually remember and you're testifying as
if you remember based on something you saw written. Alright. Yes. Translated.
That's exactly then what תוספות works out. How does that work with
the issue of translator and this whole thing? But that reflects a
reality that they couldn't always have people traveling and showing up in
court. So the rest of the תוספות works that through. Okay, let's
now look at the משנה. Mishna, ג' אחין נשואין ג' נכריות. gimel
achin nesuin gimel nochriyos. Okay, three brothers married to three unrelated women.
ומת אחד מהם. v'meis echad meihem. Okay, three brothers married to three
unrelated women and one of them dies. ועשה בה השני מאמר v'asah
bah hasheini ma'amar and we saw this case
before, and the second one did a מאמר ma'amar with this available
woman. ומת v'meis and then he died.
So here the case is
Reuven, Shimon, and
Levi.
Okay, Reuven is married to Rochel, he's married to Devorah, who should
Levi be married to? Levi's married to Chuldah. Right? So anyway, okay,
so one of the brothers died, okay, and now Shimon we decided
what blue was our מאמר ma'amar color he did מאמר ma'amar with
Rochel, okay, and then Shimon died. Okay. Now Levi here,
it doesn't really matter who Levi's married to. Okay, he has a
מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to Devorah coming from Shimon, right? He
has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to Rochel coming from Reuven,
coming from Reuven, right? He could have done יבום yibum down here
too. But since Shimon did מאמר, ma'amar, Shimon is now quasi-married to
Rochel as well, right? What's the whole status of מאמר? ma'amar? So
he also has a מצוה mitzvah of יבום yibum to Rochel, a
quasi-מצוה mitzvah from Shimon. Okay, so here he actually has a מצוה
mitzvah of יבום yibum to one woman based on two separate brothers.
Okay, so this is the this is the issue the משנה Mishna.
deals with.
So let's take a look.
הרי אלו חולצות ולא מתייבמות. harei elu choltzos v'lo misyabmos. Both women,
Devorah and Rochel, get חליצה chalitzah and not יבום. yibum. So why
Rochel is problematic we understand, why Devorah is problematic is a lot
less clear. Let's see why Rochel is problematic. שנאמר shenemar says the
verse says ומת אחד מהם v'meis echad meihem one of the brothers
dies, then יבמה יבוא עליה yevamah yavo aleha מי שעליה זיקת יבם
אחד, mi she'aleha zikas yavam echad, only a woman that he's connected
to through one of his through one brother. ולא שעליה זיקת שני
יבמין, v'lo she'aleha zikas shnei yevamin, not a woman that basically is
connected through two brother-in-laws or for from his perspective from two brothers.
So this woman Rochel is basically, if Shimon had fully married her,
Reuven would have been out of the picture if he had done
יבום. yibum. Then both of the women would have come to him
through Shimon. But since he didn't do יבום, yibum, Reuven is still
in the picture and now he's got her coming to him from
two brothers, that's excluded. Now some say that if מאמר ma'amar is
דרבנן derabbanan this whole דרשה drashah is דרבנן, derabbanan okay, but if
מאמר ma'amar has some דאורייתא d'oraisa weight like we've seen by בית
שמאי, Beis Shammai, then it's possible that Rochel could really be in
a quasi-position and still have two זיקות. zikos. Let's see the end
of the משנה. Mishna רבי שמעון אומר Rabbi Shimon omer מיבם לאיזו
שירצה וחולץ לשניה. meyabem l'eizo sheyirtzeh v'choleitz lashniyah. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
doesn't buy this. He basically says either מאמר ma'amar is as opposed
to saying מאמר ma'amar is 50%, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's
either 100% or zero. So if it's 100%, then Rochel would be
totally married to Shimon, Reuven's out of the picture, so he can
do יבום yibum to Rochel or Devorah. If מאמר ma'amar was zero,
then Rochel is not related to Shimon, coming from Reuven, and he
also could do יבום yibum with Rochel. So if it's 50% you've
got your problem, he's both Reuven and Shimon, but it's not, it's
100% or zero. Now why can't he do יבום yibum with both?
Well if מאמר ma'amar was nothing, he could do יבום yibum with
both. They're coming from different brothers. But if מאמר ma'amar worked, then
they're both coming from Shimon, and you can't do יבום yibum with
two wives from the same brother, right? You do יבום yibum with
one and then or חליצה chalitzah? and everybody else gets off. So
because it might have worked, he can only do יבום yibum with
one. Because it might not have worked, then he has to do
חליצה chalitzah. with the other. with the other woman. Okay, just doing
יבום yibum with רבקה Rivka won't be enough, because maybe מאמר maamar
didn't work and she was up here with ראובן, Reuven, and דבורה's
Devorah still waiting for something to happen. So you can't do יבום
yibum with both, because they could be coming from the same brother.
But so you have to do, and you can't just do יבום,
yibum, because they could be coming from opposite brothers. So you have
to do יבום yibum with one, חליצה chalitzah with the other. So
that's רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says it's either
a hundred or zero. תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says she's fifty percent.
So therefore יוחל Yokhel has the problem, so you know why you
gotta do חליצה chalitzah with רחל. Rachel. What you don't know is
why can't you go ahead and do יבום yibum with דבורה? Devorah?
Okay, so we'll take a look at that in the גמרא. Gemara
Yes?
You could also have this discussion for the case of יש זיקה
yesh zika when there's no מאמר. maamar.
Right. Moving on. Okay,
אי זיקה בית יבמין דאורייתא ee zika beit yevamin d'oraisa says the
גמרא. Gemara One minute. If this is a דאורייתא d'oraisa problem that
רחל Rachel has a quasi-status and this is a real פסול, pasul
so חליצה נמי לא תיבעי. chalitzah nami lo tibei. So why do
we say that רחל Rachel needs חליצה? chalitzah. If she really the
תורה's Torah excluding a woman with this double status, so then exclude
her, let her walk
off. אלא מדרבנן, ela miderabbanan, you're right. This whole idea of a
double status is only a דרבנן derabbanan problem, probably because מאמר maamar
is a whole דרבנן d'rabbanan. issue. Fine. And because the whole thing
is a דרבנן d'rabbanan, problem, we're still, you still gotta do something
with רחל, Rachel, so you still need חליצה. chalitzah. גזירה שמא יאמרו
שתי יבמות הבאות מבית אחד מתייבמות. gezeirah shema yomru shtei yevamot habaot
mibayit echad mityabmot. Because here's the point, דאורייתא d'oraisa, there's no problem
with רחל. Rachel. דאורייתא d'oraisa this is nothing. דאורייתא d'Oraisa לוי Levi
could do יבום yibum with רחל Rachel and יבום yibum with דבורה.
Devorah. But we don't like that because the way people look at
it, you know ראובן Reuven might have died ten years ago, everybody's
forgotten about ראובן, Reuven, שמעון Shimon has done קידושין with רחל, Rachel,
people think רחל's Rachel שמעון's Shimon wife, and people are going to
now see לוי Levi do יבום yibum with both. They're going to
think that a brother married to two wives, the surviving brother can
do יבום yibum with both of the wives. And that's obviously not
true. Once you do יבום yibum with one, the other wife, you
do חליצה chalitzah with one, the other wife has to, so because
people think that רחל's Rachel שמעון's Shimon wife, we don't let him
do יבום yibum with both, even though דאורייתא, de'oraita you're right, they
really are completely separate. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says we
know why you don't do יבום, yibum, we know why we're not
going to allow יבום yibum with both. We know why we're going
to demand חליצה chalitzah and we're going to situate the problem with
רחל. Rachel. So we're not going to allow יבום yibum with רחל
Rachel because
anyway she's the one that sort of is the source of this,
of this issue. So her we're going to demand חליצה. chalitzah This
פסול of שתי אחיות shtei achayot מדרבנן miderabbanan we're going to demand
חליצה. chalitzah But if as long as you say that דאורייתא this
really is, you know, there's no relationship, let him do חליצה chalitzah
with רחל Rachel and let him do יבום yibum with דבורה. Devorah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this, ונייבם לחדא ונחלוץ לחדא. v'neyabem l'chada v'nechlotz l'chada. Do יבום yibum
with one and חליצה chalitzah with the other? So the גמרא Gemara...
says no, גזירה שמא יאמרו בית אחד מקצתו בנוי ומקצתו חלוץ. gezeirah
shema yomru bayit echad miktzato banuy umiktzato chaluetz. Same problem. People will
think that both of them are his wives, and they'll think look,
he did יבום yibum with one and חליצה chalitzah with the other.
So in general, if a brother dies and has two wives, you
gotta do יבום yibum with one and חליצה chalitzah with the other.
With, you can imagine people thinking, right? There are multiple wives, so
you do יבום yibum with one and חליצה chalitzah with the other.
Okay, so we don't want people to think that. So the גמרא
Gemara says ויאמרו. v'yomru. Who cares? Let them think it. So what
are you going to do? Big deal. So you do a few
extra חליצות. chalitzot. Who cares? Okay, so great. Do יבום yibum with
one and חליצה chalitzah with the other even though you don't need,
what's the big deal? What's the cost? Not that you should do
it, but who cares if people make that mistake? גמרא Gemara says
no. אי דמיאבם והדר חליץ, ei d'miabem v'hadar chalitz, you're right. If
normally a guy died, left a few wives, and the brother does
יבום yibum with the first one and then does חליצה chalitzah, with
the others, הכי נמי, hachi nami, then okay, it was silly but
there was no cost, no loss. He did חליצה chalitzah with women
who didn't require it. Of course, maybe you'll now פסול them for
כהונה. kehuna. Okay, but even so, maybe בית דין will then know
better, but at least it won't be cost to the act of
חליצה chalitzah itself. אלא גזירה, ela gezeirah, here's the concern. If people
think you do both, דילמא חליץ ברישא והדר מיאבם. dilma chalitz be'reisha
v'hadar miyabem. First you'll do חליצה chalitzah, to the one, to the
sister-in-law he's not interested in, and then you'll do יבום yibum with
the other one. That is a problem, because once you've done the
first act of חליצה, chalitzah, you've excluded all the other wives from
יבום. yibum. וקם ליה באשר לא יבנה. v'kam lei b'asher lo yivneh.
That once he's in the category of that he is not building
up the house, then he can't marry the remaining sisters once he's
done חליצה chalitzah with, you know, sister-in-laws, once he's done חליצה chalitzah,
with one. ורחמנא אמר, כיוון שלא בנה, keivan shelo banah, once, once
he doesn't build once, once he does חליצה, chalitzah שוב לא יבנה.
shuv lo yivneh. Okay, now you could say, okay, so I get
that this רחל Rachel looks like שמעון's Shimon wife, and because looks
like שמעון's Shimon wife, we're not going to allow him to do
יבום yibum with both. We're not going to allow him to do
יבום yibum and חליצה, chalitzah, because that'll lead to another case of
two wives where people will do יבום yibum and חליצה chalitzah and
if they do it in the wrong order, you got a problem.
But we are going to demand is two חליצות, chalitzot, because that
comes with no cost. Because what will happen? Another brother will die
with five wives, so you do five חליצות. chalitzot. Okay, big deal,
right? I mean, the cost might be the כהונה kehuna issue, but
the act of חליצה, chalitzah בית דין hopefully again will know better,
but the act of חליצה chalitzah. will come at no cost. So
the גמרא Gemara is explaining why the משנה mishna. frames it as
a type of a דאורייתא problem with רחל Rachel having a dual
status. A, that wouldn't explain why רחל Rachel gets חליצה, chalitzah and
B, it wouldn't explain why you can't do יבום yibbum with דבורה.
Devorah. So the גמרא Gemara therefore reframes it as a גזירה gezeira
that they both look like ראובן Reuven's wife, and the only way
to play it safe in that case, I mean שמעון Shimon's wife,
and the only way to play it safe is to do חליצה
chalitzah with both. Okay, now the גמרא...
Gemara Why can't you do יבום yibbum with דבורה? Devorah?
Because then people, that's exactly what it said, then the next time
somebody will do יבום yibbum with one wife and חליצה chalitzah, with
the other and they'll do it in the wrong order and whatever.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. אמר רבא, Amar Rava, נתן
גט למאמרו. nasan get l'maamaro. So now we're going to deal with,
so now we got this down. Now רבא says let's say the
guy came
and gave, after מאמר, maamar, remember מאמר maamar's an act of קידושין,
it's really giving כסף and saying הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at
mekudeshes li, it's just in the context of יבום, yibbum, so therefore
it's called מאמר maamar so you don't think it's מדאורייתא m'd'Oraisa working.
So he gave, he did a מאמר maamar with רחל. Rachel. Now
before he dies, you know what he did? He decided he's no
longer interested in רחל Rachel and he gave her a גט. get.
Okay? And then he dies. Okay, is רחל Rachel now out of
the picture and לוי Levi free to do יבום yibbum with דבורה?
Devorah? Maybe לוי Levi should be even free to do יבום yibbum
with רחל Rachel because she goes back to being waiting for יבום
yibbum or חליצה. chalitzah Okay? So let's take a look. אמר רבא,
נתן גט למאמרו, nasan get l'maamaro, he gave a גט get to
contradict his מאמר, maamar, to counteract I should say, הותרה צרתה. hutra
tzarasah. So the co-wife דבורה Devorah becomes available. אבל היא, aval hi,
רחל, Rachel, אסורה. asura. He can't do יבום. yibbum. He still has
to do חליצה chalitzah. obviously because she still hasn't had יבום yibbum
or חליצה chalitzah. done, but he can't do יבום. yibbum. Why? דמיחלפא
בבעלת גט. d'michalfa b'baalas get. Because people will confuse it for a
case of a woman who received a גט get on the זיקה.
zika. So here's the הלכה. Okay, you if the guy did a
מאמר maamar and wants to now separate, he needs גט get and
חליצה, chalitzah. the גט for the מאמר maamar and the חליצה chalitzah
for the זיקה. zika. If he didn't do a מאמר maamar and
he doesn't want to, you know, to be with this woman, he
does חליצה. chalitza? That's all that's required, that's all that's asked. But
he has the option of even if he didn't do מאמר, maamar,
he has the option of giving her a גט as well. And
that גט, it's called a גט לזיקה, get l'zika, not a גט
למאמר, get l'maamar, and that גט basically says I'm
preventing the possibility of חליצה. chalitza. I gave, it's Rabbinic, but the
גט is against the זיקה, zika, not against the מאמר, maamar, and
it excludes the possibility of יבום yibbum from that point on.
He'd still need חליצה. He would still need חליצה afterwards. It's only
דרבנן. derabbanan. It's only דרבנן, derabbanan right. Okay, I can't explain the
circumstances, but there's some case where that'll be important. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says איכא דאמרי, icha d'amri, some say אמר רבא, נתן
גט למאמרו, nasan get l'maamaro, הותרה אפילו היא, hutra afilu hi, even
רחל Rachel can now get יבום. yibbum. מאי טעמא? mai taama? Why?
מה דעבד בה שקליה, ma d'avad bah shaklei, what he did to
her, the מאמר, maamar, he took away, and we only, we see
it as completely neutralizing, we don't see it as now changing her
status and looking at her as a בעלת הגט. baalas haget. No,
it only removed the מאמר. maamar. Now of course the question is
how do you decide whether the גט is addressed just to the
מאמר maamar or also to the זיקה? zika? So רש"י Rashi basically
says it just depends on what you say when you do it.
Look at רש"י, Rashi, this little רש"י Rashi here where he says,
he says
מה דעבד שקליה, ma d'avad shaklei, it's like across from the next
משנה, mishna like two lines down. So מה דעבד שקליה ma d'avad
shaklei says רש"י... Rashi... דהוי כמו שלא עשה בה מאמר ועשה מספק
בה משולשת מחמת זיקת
אחיו הראשון ודווקא שפירש למאמרו ולא לזיקתו.
de'havei k'mo she'lo asa ba maamar ve'asa misafek ba meshuleshet
machmat zikat achiv harishon vedavka sheperesh le'maamaro velo le'zikato. He has to
say: this גט is only to counteract the מאמר, maamar, not to
negate the זיקה. zika. אבל סתמא קיימא ולא יבנה כלו אחים. aval
stama kaima velo yivne kulu achim. A סתם stam גט is assumed
to be going on the זיקה zika as well and to prevent
anybody from doing יבום. yibum. Okay. In the document?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Is it orally or in the document? I'm not sure. But given
that it's so amorphous, you understand רבא's first position much better, right?
It's so unclear whether this is a גט just for the מאמר
maamar or is this a גט for the זיקה. zika. So actually
in some ways normally all the דרבננ׳ס derabbanans and the גזירות gezeiras
seem to us a little far-fetched. Here of all places, it makes
a lot of sense to say it's not so clear whether this
is a גט for the מאמר maamar or a גט for the
זיקה. zika. Then just allow it to be גט.
If they give a גט to the זיקה, zika, why do they
still require חליצה?
This is only דרבנן.
So then just allow it to be גט.
The גט. The גט has no meaning the same way קידושין has
no meaning דאורייתא by a יבום yibum case. That's why it's מאמר.
maamar. So the only thing the תורה Torah recognizes in this circumstance
is יבום yibum or חליצה.
But why wouldn't the דרבנן give the גט the same status as
מאמר? maamar?
They do. They do.
So the same way מאמר maamar makes her married, then the גט
should give...
Yeah, but מאמר maamar doesn't fully make her married. That's all the
discussions we've been having. It puts her in a quasi status.
Okay. All right. Next משנה. שני אחים. shnei achim. We are not
getting any more caught up. שני אחים נשואים שתי אחיות ומת אחד
מהן. shnei achim nesuim shtei achayot umet echad mehen. Two brothers, two
married to two sisters, and one dies. ואחר כך מתה אשתו של
שני. ve'achar kach meta ishto shel sheni. Okay, so this is an
easy case. And then the wife of the second one dies. So
here is, this is the whole question about the ערוה, erva, you
know, the the case where, okay, ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon get
married to רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah.
Okay, so ראובן Reuven dies. What's רחל's Rachel status?
אחות אשה. achot isha. ערוה. erva. Goodbye. Walk off. But then לאה
Leah died. Oh, maybe she's no longer אחות אשה. achot isha. Maybe
you can go ahead and do יבום. yibum. No, because she was
אחות אשה achot isha at the moment that the יבום yibum became
relevant, that's her husband died, that's the status that remains. That's what
the משנה says. ואחר כך מתה אשתו של שני הרי זו אסורה
עליו לעולם. ve'achar kach meta ishto shel sheni harei zu asura alav
le'olam. רחל Rachel remains eternally forbidden. הואיל ונאסרה עליו שעה אחת ho'il
venasra alav sha'a achat because at that critical moment, actually it says
at any moment, but we can even emphasize that the critical moment,
the initial moment, she was forbidden to שמעון. Shimon. So the גמרא
Gemara says פשיטא. pishita. This is obvious. השתא ומה התם דלא מדחיא
מהאי ביתא לגמרי hashta uma hatam d'lo midchaya mehai beita legamrei
when she was not completely put away from the household, you might
remember that we have the case, it was only yesterday I think,
where there were three brothers, right? ראובן, Reuven, שמעון, Shimon, and לוי.
Levi. And here you have רחל Rachel and לאה. Leah. And what
happens is ראובן Reuven dies.
Then what happens?
Hold on.
I know.
One minute.
Oh, right.
And then לוי Levi marries רחל, Rachel, okay? And then what happens?
So לוי Levi marries רחל. Rachel. Oh, שמעון Shimon at this stage,
right as ראובן Reuven died, okay, רחל Rachel is what's her status?
רחל Rachel is אחות אשה achot isha to שמעון Shimon and totally
okay to לוי, Levi, right? And then לוי Levi goes ahead and
marries her and then does יבום. yibum. לאה Leah dies. לוי Levi
dies. שמעון Shimon remains forbidden. Why does שמעון Shimon remain forbidden? Because
at that early stage she was אחות אשה achot isha to him,
at that early status. So here the גמרא is saying if this
case is a problem, then of course this case is a problem.
I mean, you know, here even though her relationship to שמעון Shimon
was problematic, it wasn't problematic to לוי, Levi, so she was still
somewhat in the פרשה parsha here. Here, there's only one brother, she's
completely אסורה asura to שמעון. Shimon. Of course she's going to remain
אסורה. asura. Okay? So that's the גמרא's question. ומה התם דלא מדחיא
מהאי ביתא לגמרי uma hatam d'lo midchaya mehai beita legamrei when she's
not completely pushed away from that family because לוי Levi is still,
she's still מותר mutar to לוי, Levi, אמרת לא amarta lo that
she's forbidden to שמעון Shimon because at one stage she was forbidden
to שמעון. Shimon. So הכא דקא מדחיא מהאי ביתא לגמרי hacha d'ka
midchaya mehai beita legamrei here that as soon as ראובן Reuven dies,
she's completely out of the פרשה, parsha, no brothers, she's not relevant
to any brothers, she walks away, she's out of the פרשה, parsha,
so therefore לא כל שכן? lo kol sheken? Of course this case
is going to be permissible, I mean forbidden. She's going to be
forbidden to do it and therefore she can just walk away. So
the גמרא says you're right. תנא היי תנא ברישא. tana hai tana
be'reisha. This case was taught first. This is the more obvious case
that רחל Rachel remains forbidden.
והך חזיא ליה ve'hach chazya lei and initially the גמרא thought the
תנא tana thought... that this case might be מותר, mutar, because she
wasn't completely out of the פרשה. parsha. Maybe after לוי Levi marries
her, her status changes. Okay? So ושרי, ve-shari, he thought that it
was מותר, mutar, והדר חזא ליה לאסור, ve-hadar chaza lei le-issor, and
then he decided no, this case is also אסור. assur. She was
אסורה asura once to שמעון, Shimon, she remains אסורה asura to שמעון.
Shimon. Okay? ואיידי, ve-ayedi, so really once you decided this was אסור,
assur, you didn't need to teach this משנה. ואיידי דחביבא ליה אקדמה,
ve-ayedi de-chaviva lei akdama, because this was a nice big חידוש, chiddush,
we put this case first, which made, we had the same idea
before, which makes this superfluous. ומשנה לא זזה ממקומה, u-mishna lo zaza
mi-mekoma, and therefore we didn't remove this משנה even though now it
became superfluous and obvious.
Why'd they do that? גמרא is always saying צריכותא.
tzrichuta. Yeah, but sometimes it says זו אין צריך לומר זו, zu
ein tzarich lomar zu, so this is a variation on that.